A Guide to the Western Lunatic Asylum [Staunton, Virginia] Collection, 1840-1903 (bulk 1840-1868)
Special Collections, Virginia Tech
Special Collections, Virginia Tech
Western Lunatic Asylum [Staunton, Virginia] Collection, 1840-190 (bulk 1840-1868)
Special Collections, Virginia Tech, Blacksburg, Va.
Ms2016-021
0.6 Cubic Feet 1 box; 1 oversize folder
The Western Lunatic Asylum Collection includes correspondence written to the Western Lunatic Asylum in Staunton, Virginia, dating from 1840 through the late 19th century, as well as annual reports from the 1860s and 1900s.
Access Restrictions
The collection is open for research.
Acquisition Information
The Western Lunatic Asylum [Staunton, Virginia] Collection was purchased in three separate accession between August and November of 2016. Additional materials were acquired in 2017, 2018, and 2019. Additional letters may be received in the future.
Historical Note
Originally called the Western State Lunatic Asylum, the Western Lunatic Asylum was a hospital for the mentally ill in Staunton, Virginia, opening in 1828. In its early years, the institution was a resort-style asylum, directed under Dr. Francis T. Stribling. Dr. Stribling promoted a clean, healthy, and kind atmosphere that would aid in the healing process of his patients. While Dr. Stribling was the director of the hospital, patients were well cared for and treated with respect.
Scope and Content
The Western Lunatic Asylum Collection includes correspondence written to the Western Lunatic Asylum in Staunton, Virginia, dating from 1840 to about 1870, as well as final year reports from 1862 and 1903. The correspondece relates to the Western Lunatic Asylum in Staunton, Virginia, and most of the letters are written to Dr. Francis T. Stribling, the director of the Western Lunatic Asylum, by family members of patients concerning their care. One of the letters isn't written to Dr. Stribling, but he is mentioned in the letter.
Arrangement
The correspondence in this collection is arranged in chronological order. The annual reports are in a separate folder.
Index Terms
Subjects:
Folk, historical, and patent medicine; Health; Local/Regional History and Appalachian South; Medicine
Geographical Names:
Staunton (Va.)
Persons:
Stribling, Francis T. (Francis Taliaferro), 1810-1874
Corporate Names:
Western Lunatic Asylum (Va.) (1828-?)
Contents List
- Correspondence, 1840-1868, n.d.
  - Undated correspondence (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - 1840-1844 (Box 1, Folder 3, Oversize 1)
  - 1845-1849 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - 1850-1851 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - 1852 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - 1853 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - 1854 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - 1855 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - 1856 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - 1857 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - 1858 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - 1859 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - 1868 (Box 1, Folder 14)
- Annual Reports, 1862, 1903
  - Report to the President and Directors of the Central Lunatic Asylum for the Fiscal Year 1861-2 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Seventy-Sixth Annual Report of the Board of Directors and of the Superintendent of the Western State Hospital of Virginia, 1903 (Box 1, Folder 1)